# Esben Høegholm Lykke

#### PHD STUDENT

SDU. Odense

■ sesben@hotmail.com | ② esbenlykke | 🛅 esben-lykke | 💆 Esben\_lykke

### Intro\_

My name is Esben and I love diving into the world of data and getting lost in intriguing challenges. I have experience with scientific writing, crunching numbers with statistical analysis, visualizing data, exploring the wonders of machine learning, and sharing knowledge through teaching. On top of that, I've got a knack for project management and research methodologies.

When it comes to data-wrangling, R is my trusty sidekick. But hey, I'm no stranger to Python, Matlab, and SQL either. So, let's have some fun with data together!

## **Education**

#### **University of Southern Denmark**

Odense, Denmark

PHD IN EXERCISE EPIDEMIOLOGY

October 2023

My work centers around creating methodologies that leverage machine learning techniques to detect non-wear and sleep periods in accelerometer data. This allows for the prediction of sleep quality metrics on a population level. My project is supervised by Associate Professor Jan Christian Brand

Aarhus University

Aarhus, Denmark

MS IN SPORTS SCIENCE, HUMAN PHYSIOLOGY

January 2017

 MS Thesis: Unprompted Vigorous Physical Activity is Associated With Higher Levels of Subsequent Sedentary Behaviour in Participants With Low Cardiorespiratory Fitness: a Cross-Sectional Study

**Aarhus University**Aarhus, Denmark

BS IN SPORTS SCIENCE

June 2014

BS Thesis: The Strech-Shortening-Cycle in Plyometric Exercise Training

## **Relevant employments**

#### **Aarhus University, Department of Sport Science**

Aarhus, DK

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2018 - 2019

· Analyses of accelerometer data and manuscript writing on two research projects supervised by Professor Kristian Overgaard.

## University of Southern Denmark, Department of Sports Science and Clinical Biomechanics

Odense, DK

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

2019 - 2020

• Worked on systematic reviews as a member of the INTERLIVES consortium and prepared my PhD project.

## **Teaching experience**

I have been/am an instructor on the following courses.

2023 **PhD course**: Data Science Skills for Health Researchers Using R and the Tidyverse (SDU)

2022-23 **MS course**: Data Science in Health Science (SDU)

2020-22 **BS course**: Applied Statistics (SDU)

2020 **BS course**: Project Managment with External Partner (SDU)

2020 **BS course**: Public health projects in practice (SDU)

## **Publications**

Skovgaard, E. L., Roswall, M. A., Pedersen, N. H., Larsen, K. T., Grøntved, A., & Brønd, J. C. (2023). Generalizability and performance of methods to detect non-wear with free-living accelerometer recordings. Scientific Reports, 13(1), 2496. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-29666-x

- 2. Mühlen, J. M., Stang, J., Skovgaard, E. L., Judice, P. B., Molina-Garcia, P., Johnston, W., Sardinha, L. B., Ortega, F. B., Caulfield, B., Bloch, W., Cheng, S., Ekelund, U., Brønd, J. C., Grøntved, A., & Schumann, M. (2021). Recommendations for determining the validity of consumer wearable heart rate devices: Expert statement and checklist of the INTERLIVE network. *British Journal of Sports Medicine*, 55(14), 767–779. https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2020-103148
- 3. Johnston, W., Judice, P. B., García, P. M., Mühlen, J. M., Skovgaard, E. L., Stang, J., Schumann, M., Cheng, S., Bloch, W., Brønd, J. C., Ekelund, U., Grøntved, A., Caulfield, B., Ortega, F. B., & Sardinha, L. B. (2021). Recommendations for determining the validity of consumer wearable and smartphone step count: Expert statement and checklist of the INTERLIVE network. *British Journal of Sports Medicine*, 55(14), 780–793. https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2020-103147
- 4. Skovgaard, E. L., Pedersen, J., Møller, N. C., Grøntved, A., & Brønd, J. C. (2021). Manual annotation of time in bed using free-living recordings of accelerometry data. *Sensors*, 21(24), 8442. https://doi.org/10.3390/s21248442
- 5. Pedersen, K. K., Skovgaard, E. L., Larsen, R., Stengaard, M., Sørensen, S., & Overgaard, K. (2019). The applicability of thigh-worn vs. Hipworn ActiGraph accelerometers during walking and running. *Journal for the Measurement of Physical Behaviour*, 2(4), 209–217. https://doi.org/10.1123/jmpb.2018-0043
- 6. Skovgaard, E. L., Obling, K., Maindal, H. T., Rasmussen, C., & Overgaard, K. (2019). Unprompted vigorous physical activity is associated with higher levels of subsequent sedentary behaviour in participants with low cardiorespiratory fitness: A cross-sectional study. European Journal of Sport Science, 19(7), 1004–1013. https://doi.org/10.1080/17461391.2019.1574905